Guide to the Alexander Metcalf Fisher Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alexander Metcalf Fisher Papers
1803-1898
1809-1822
GEN MSS 1473
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.8
(16 boxes) + 1 art
The Alexander Metcalf Fisher papers consist of correspondence, scientific and personal writings, school notes, eulogies, and other material by or about the Yale College student (Class of 1813) and Yale professor. Drafts and calculations for articles on mathematics, physics, astronomy, and other subjects published between 1817 and 1822, as well as scripts for forty lectures in natural philosophy, illustrate Fisher's academic career in the context of contemporary scientific learning. Documenting the social, economic, religious, and emotional life of a young man living in New England during the Early Republic are extensive correspondence written by Fisher to his parents from 1809-1821, and eight personal and travel diaries. Correspondents also include other relatives, the Fisher family's pastor Nathanael Emmons, and Yale affiliates. Also contained in the collection is a portrait of Fisher engraved on copper by Simeon Smith Jocelyn.
Fisher, Alexander Metcalf, 1794-1822
Jocelyn, Simeon Smith, 1799-1879
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Willard J. Fisher, 1921.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1809-1825. II. Writings, 1803-1822. III. Personal and Family Papers, 1813-1898.
Biographical / Historical
Alexander Metcalf Fisher was born in 1794 in Franklin, Massachusetts, to Caleb Fisher (1768-1862) and Sarah Cushing Fisher (1771-1835). Fisher studied at Yale College from 1809-1813, and at the Andover Theological Seminary in 1814, before returning to Yale in 1815 to serve as a tutor. He was later promoted to Adjunct Professor (1817) and Full Professor (1819) of Mathematics and Natural Philosophy. Before his premature death in the wreck of the ship Albion on 1822 April 22, Fisher was engaged to women's education advocate Catharine Esther Beecher (1800-1878).
Scope and Contents
The Alexander Metcalf Fisher papers consist of correspondence, scientific and personal writings, school notes, eulogies, and other material by or about the Yale College student (Class of 1813) and Yale professor. Drafts and calculations for articles on mathematics, physics, astronomy, and other subjects published between 1817 and 1822, as well as scripts for forty lectures in natural philosophy, illustrate Fisher's academic career in the context of contemporary scientific learning. Documenting the social, economic, religious, and emotional life of a young man living in New England during the Early Republic are extensive correspondence written by Fisher to his parents from 1809-1821, and eight personal and travel diaries. Correspondents also include other relatives, the Fisher family's pastor Nathanael Emmons, and Yale affiliates. Also contained in the collection is a portrait of Fisher engraved on copper by Simeon Smith Jocelyn.
Separated Materials
Thirteen printed items received with the collection, consisting largely of sermons, religious pamphlets, eulogies, and scientific texts, were removed for separate cataloging in April 2018. In the library's online catalog, those items are identified by the local note "From the Alexander Metcalf Fisher Papers", and the subject heading "Fisher, Alexander Metcalf, 1794-1822 -- Ownership". They can be found in the catalog by searching the phrase "Fisher, Alexander Metcalf" in the Special Collections Subject field.
College teachers -- Connecticut -- New Haven; College teachers -- Religious life -- Connecticut -- New Haven; College students -- Connecticut -- New Haven; College students -- Massachusetts -- Andover; Physics -- Study and teaching -- Connecticut -- New Haven; New Haven (Conn.) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Commonplace books -- United States -- 19th century; Copper engravings (visual works) -- United States -- 19th century; Diaries -- United States -- 19th century; Lectures -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- 19th century; College teachers -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- 19th century; Beecher, Catharine Esther, 1800-1878; Beecher, Edward, 1803-1895; Day, Jeremiah, 1773-1867; Emmons, Nathanael, 1745-1840; Fisher, Alexander Metcalf, 1794-1822; Fisher, Caleb, 1768-1862; Fisher, Sarah Cushing, 1771-1835; Fisher, Willard, 1796-1866; Andover Theological Seminary -- Students; Yale College (1718-1887) -- Faculty; Yale College (1718-1887) -- Religion; Yale College (1718-1887) -- Students
- Correspondence, 1809-1825; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. comprises correspondence to and from Fisher, family members, friends, and Yale affiliates. The bulk of the correspondence consists of letters sent by Fisher to his parents Caleb and Sarah over a period of thirteen years. Other correspondents include Fisher's siblings Nancy and Willard; Congregational minister Nathanael Emmons (1745-1840); theologian Edward Beecher (1803-1895), brother to Fisher's fiancée; President of Yale College Jeremiah Day (1773-1867); and Yale College Professor James Luce Kingsley (1778-1852). Most of the third-party correspondence documents the aftermath of Fisher's loss at sea in April 1822.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by sender.
  - Beecher, Edward to Caleb Fisher, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Two letters regarding the settlement of Alexander Metcalf Fisher's estate, particularly the sale of his books.
  - Beecher, Edward to Willard Fisher, 1824-1825 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Three letters written during Beecher's studies in Andover discussing Willard Fisher's religious feelings, and personal and family news.
  - Day, Jeremiah to Nathanael Emmons, 1822-05-29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Day, Jeremiah to Caleb Fisher, 1822-06-11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Emmons, Nathanael to Alexander Metcalf Fisher, 1811-01-02 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Letter of advice for Fisher's conduct at Yale.
  - Fisher, Alexander Metcalf to Jeremiah Day, 1815-09-22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fisher, Alexander Metcalf to Caleb and Sarah Fisher, 1809-1821 (Box 1, Folder 7-18)
    Fifty-seven letters sent to his parents from New Haven, Connecticut, and from Andover, Massachussets, discussing his education, work as tutor and professor, health, financial needs, and family news.
  - Fisher, Alexander Metcalf to Nancy Fisher, 1818-1821 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Seven letters to his sister regarding her education, reading, and letter writing.
  - Fisher, Alexander Metcalf to James Luce Kingsley, 1815, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes a letter from aboard ship Albion, possibly Fisher's last extent correspondence.
  - Fisher, Alexander Metcalf to Princeton University, 1821-10-19 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Letter draft regarding a position offer at Princeton.
  - Fisher, Alexander Metcalf to unidentified editors, drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fisher, Alexander Metcalf to unidentified correspondent, 1820-03-23 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Kingsley, James Luce to Caleb Fisher, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Two letters, including a transcription of a witness account of the Albion shipwreck.
- Writings, 1803-1822; Series II; 3.5; (13 boxes)
  Organized into five subseries: Diaries, Scientific Articles, Lecture Scripts, Notes and Learning Exercises, and Other Writings. Files within subseries are arranged alphabetically.
  Series II. contains holograph texts documenting Fisher's personal life, education, and academic work, in the form of diaries, article drafts, notebooks, commonplace books, lecture scripts, learning exercises, and school essays compiled during his primary schooling, collegiate education, and tenure as a Professor of Mathematics and Natural Philosophy at Yale College.
  - Diaries, 1813-1820
    - "Brief heads of the plans begun & accomplished during 4 days past", 1815-1817 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Short diary recorded in September 1815, followed by a twenty-four page commentary added in May 1817 on his mental health state during the recording of the original entry two years prior.
    - Personal notes, circa 1815 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Religious diaries, 1815-1819; 3 (Box 2, Folder 27-29)
    - Travel diary through Vermont, 1813-10-04 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Travel diary from Litchfield, Connecticut, to Schenectady, New York, 1818-09 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Travel diary through Rhode Island and Connecticut, circa 1818 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Travel diary "Journal to Philadelphia", circa 1820 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Scientific Articles, 1818-1821
    - Annotations to the article "The Compressibility of Water" by Jacob Perkins, 1821 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Published in the American Journal of Science and Arts 3, no.2 (May 1821).
    - "Essay on musical temperament", circa 1818 (Box 3, Folder 35-37)
      Published in the American Journal of Science and Arts 1 (1819).
    - Letters to the editors of The Microscope, 1820 and undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Notebook containing reviews and other texts, circa 1817-1821 (Box 12)
      Bound manuscript containing solutions to mathematical problems published in contemporary journals, commentaries on the Gospels, solar eclipse calculations, notes titled "An improved method for solving some cases of maxima and minima" possibly relating to Fisher's published article on function extrema, and reviews of Jeremiah Day's A course of mathematics " (published in Analectic Magazine IX (June 1817)) and of Memoirs of the Connecticut Academy of Science.
    - "Observations con[cerning] the management of algebraical problems", undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Accompanied by a letter to Yale professor and editor of the American Journal of Science and Arts Benjamin Silliman, in Fisher's hand, forwarding a Diophantine problem solution by professor Theodore Strong of Hamilton College, and by various mathematical equations.
    - "Observations on the comet of 1819" (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - "On maxima & minima of functions of two variable quantities", 1818-08 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      Published in the American Journal of Science and Arts 5, no. 1 (1822).
    - "On some recent improvements in the construction of the printing press", circa 1821 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      Published in the American Journal of Science and Arts 3, no.2 (1821).
    - "Remarks on Dr. Enfield's Institutes of Natural Philosophy", circa 1820 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      Published in the American Journal of Science and Arts 3, no.1 (1821).
    - Review of William Tudor's Letters on the Eastern States, circa 1821 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Lecture Scripts, circa 1818-1822
    The lectures in natural philosophy comprise forty sequential volumes, each containing the script of a lecture on the recto, with citations on the verso. Topics covered include gravitation, motion, pneumatics, electricity, optics, and magnetism.
    - Addresses to the Connecticut Academy [of Arts and Science] and to the Yale College junior class, 1818 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "Lectures on magnetism etc", undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Lectures in natural philosophy, no. I-XIII, circa 1818-1822 (Box 4, Folder 47-59)
    - Lectures in natural philosophy, no. XIV-XXVIII, circa 1818-1822 (Box 5, Folder 60-74)
    - Lectures in natural philosophy, no. XXIX-XL, circa 1818-1822 (Box 6, Folder 75-86)
  - Notes and Learning Exercises, 1803-1822
    Arranged alphabetically by title, when present, or by discipline.
    Topical groupings may include notes from lectures, sermons, and publications; calculations; and short essays in response to question prompts.
    - Astronomy, undated (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Bibliographies of scientific publications, circa 1822 (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Chemistry (1 of 2), circa 1812-1814 (Box 13)
      First of two volumes covering 113 lectures attended by Fisher starting in 1812.
    - Chemistry (2 of 2), circa 1812-1814 (Box 14)
      Second of two volumes covering 113 lectures attended by Fisher starting in 1812. The second volume also contains transcriptions of Timothy Dwight's farewell address to the senior class of Yale College (circa 1814) and of remarks by Dwight on William Paley's philosophy.
    - "A collection of phrases, containing many of the most common idiomatic expressions in the Latin language", undated (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - "A commonplace book according to Locke's method", 1817-06 (Box 15)
    - "Discussions on religion", undated (Box 6, Folder 90)
      Includes commentaries on theological works by William Paley and Charles Leslie.
    - Eclipse calculations and astronomical observations, circa 1819-1820 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Education, undated (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - Electricity, undated (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - "Facts and Sentiments on select topics", undated (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - French grammar, undated (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - Geography, undated (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Government and society, 1810, 1811, and undated (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - "Heads of directions for accurate and expressive singing", undated (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - "Heads of sermons", 1818-1819 (Box 7, Folder 99)
      Notes on sermons delivered by Mr. Fitch, Mr. Beecher, Mr. Taylor, and Dr. Worcester.
    - Hebrew grammar, circa 1810 (Box 7, Folder 100-102)
    - Italian grammar, undated (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Latin orations, 1812 and undated (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Mathematics, undated (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Mechanics, undated (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - "Miscellaneous hints on improvements in the arts", undated (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - "Miscellaneous remarks on Locke's essay", 1816-10 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Musical theory commonplace book, undated (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - Music notations, undated (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Natural philosophy, undated (Box 7, Folder 111-112)
    - "Notes from Biot's Magnetism", undated (Box 7, Folder 113)
    - Notes in shorthand, undated (Box 7, Folder 114)
    - Notes, miscellaneous, undated (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Notebook, miscellaneous, circa 1814-1819 (Box 16)
      Containing lecture notes, passages from theological and scholarly works, and other notes, including twenty pages titled "Public lectures on Christian theology by Dr. Woods" (presumably Leonard Woods (1774-1854), professor at Andover Theological Seminary), and "State of the philosophical apparatus of Yale College May 27, 1818", a seven page account of the scientific equipment procured by Yale College between 1769 and 1819 with their prices in pounds.
    - "On language", undated (Box 8, Folder 116-118)
    - "On the origins of springs", 1812-07 (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - Optics, undated (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Physical sciences commonplace book, undated (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - "A practical arithmetic in manuscript", 1805-1806; 2 (Box 8, Folder 122-123)
    - "A practical arithmetic in manuscript", 1807 (Box 17)
    - "Remarks on tunes in the Lock Hospital", undated (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Sketch of laboratory apparatus, undated (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Sunspot calculations, undated (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - Theology, essays, undated (Box 8, Folder 127-130)
    - Theology, notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 131-132)
    - "What are the fundamental rules of interpretation of Scriptures?", thesis for examination, 1815-09 (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Writing exercise, 1803 (Box 8, Folder 134)
  - Other Writings, 1820 and undated
    - By-laws of the Harmonic Society of New Haven County, 1820 (Box 8, Folder 135)
    - "The death of Dr. B.", undated (Box 8, Folder 136)
    - "Journey to the moon or some of the planets", fiction piece, undated (Box 8, Folder 137)
- Personal and Family Papers, 1813-1898; Series III; 1.88; (2 boxes) + 1 art
  Arranged alphabetically by document type.
  Series III. holds manuscript and printed items relating to Fisher, his fiancé Catharine Esther Beecher, and his siblings Willard, Nancy, and Sally. Of note are clippings, eulogies, and poems in memory of Fisher, and records of his Yale College graduation, as well as a copper plate engraved with a portrait of Fisher by Simeon Smith Jocelyn.
  - Almanac by Willard Fisher, manuscript, 1820, 1824 (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - Article by D. Olmstead, "Anecdotes of Prof. Fisher", manuscript, undated (Box 9, Folder 139)
    Published in The New Englander, no. IV (October 1843) as "Reminiscences of Alexander Metcalf Fisher".
  - Clippings concerning the death of Alexander Metcalf Fisher, [1822] (Box 9, Folder 140)
  - Clippings concerning the death of Catharine Esther Beecher, 1878 (Box 9, Folder 141)
  - Eclipse projections by Willard Fisher, manuscript, circa 1830 (Box 9, Folder 142)
  - Manuscript volume "Miscellaneous articles relating to the history, character & death of Prof. Fisher", undated (Box 9, Folder 143)
    Includes an extract from a sermon by Nathanael Emmons preached on 1822 June 9, songs from Fisher's funerals, tombstone inscriptions, poems, and transcriptions of two letters recounting the shipwreck of the Albion.
  - Minutes of two meetings [of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, New Haven Chapter?], circa 1880-1890 (Box 9, Folder 144)
  - Obituary for Alexander Metcalf Fisher, undated (Box 9, Folder 145)
    Manuscript copy of text published in the Christian Herald and Seaman's Magazine.
  - Obituary notice for Nancy Fisher Kidder, 1898 (Box 9, Folder 146)
  - Poems by Catharine Esther Beecher addressed to Sally Fisher, manuscript, undated (Box 9, Folder 147)
  - Poem by [?] Colton, "To the memory of Prof. Fisher", manuscript, 1823 (Box 9, Folder 148)
  - Poem "To the memory of A.M. Fisher", manuscript, undated (Box 9, Folder 149)
  - Portrait of Alexander Metcalf Fisher, copper plate engraving, after 1822 (Box 9, Folder 152)
    Engraving on copper plate by Simeon Smith Jocelyn, based on a painting by Samuel Finley Breese Morse. Caption "Prof. Alex. M. Fisher of Y. Coll. Lost in the Albion April 22nd 1822". 23 x 14 cm.
  - Trunk, unknown (Box 11 (Art))
    Late 18th-century or 19th-century dome-top wood trunk covered in decorative paper. 23 (height) x 44 (width) x 26 (depth) cm.
  - Wallpaper from the Fisher homestead in Franklin, Massachusetts, undated (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 153)
  - Yale College diploma of Alexander Metcalf Fisher, B.A., 1813 (Box 9, Folder 150)
  - Yale College "Scheme of the exercises, at the public commencement", printed handbill, 1813-09-01 (Box 9, Folder 151)
  - Yale College student list, printed handbill, circa 1815 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 154)